Heat. Heat.
Heat.
[music]
>> [music]
>> Heat. Heat.
[music]
>> [music]
>> Hey,
hey, hey.
Oh, are we live?
>> I think we're live.
>> Okay, guys, we're live. Welcome to
Living Mana Church. Sorry about the
technical difficulties. Um, and happy
new year. Happy new year. Please put in
the chat where you are viewing from. Uh,
so we could say a special welcome to
you. Also, many of you are wondering, is
it really is it pastor is this not a
replay? This is January 3rd, 2026, and
we are here. We just had technical
difficulties. Uh, so we apologize for
coming to you uh late. Uh, we will be
doing question and answer Sabbath today
and we will get to the some of the
questions you asked last week or sent in
last week uh where we weren't actually
live answering those questions. So, we
look forward to that. But, please let us
know where you're uh viewing from. share
this link. Invite people to church. We
would love to um see more ones um in our
in our chat just because you have
invited someone to church that hasn't
worshiped with us before. So, please put
where you're viewing from. We want to
say a special welcome to you. Put a one
if this is your very first time and I am
missing some of your spots. I see
Trinidad and Tobago. Welcome, Annayia.
It's always good to to see you here.
When we were off air, I saw somebody
saying, "Happy Sabbath from Serbia or
Eastern Serbia, I think. Welcome. Happy
Sabbath to you. Good to have you here."
And so, we are just so happy to have all
of you here. And if I have missed some
of you, I have Jennifer from Tennessee.
Welcome to Living Mana Church. It's good
to see you here today as well. We're
just so thankful to have all of you
here. Minnesota, welcome. Good to see
you here. and North Carolina. Good to
see you uh viewing from North Carolina.
You may not be from North Carolina, but
you're viewing from North Carolina, so
that's good. Welcome to Living Man
Church.
>> We want to wish you guys a happy
[clears throat and snorts]
new year. Um we uh are actually just
coming from Texas.
>> Yeah, we're coming from Texas.
>> And uh we were out there with uh with
family.
>> Yes.
>> And uh we're back. Yes, we are back.
>> And if you're wondering why my voice in
particular may sound uh extra
uh bassy right now, it is because
>> I'm getting over a cold.
>> So,
uh yeah, keep my voice in prayer.
>> And because he's getting over a cold, I
was able to fight off the cold, but it's
it has come upon me. So, I don't feel
well either. But I just sound better
than you do.
>> But we're here.
>> But [laughter] we're here. So we're
we're happy to be here with you. I've
seen some more places. Dylan, South
Carolina, welcome. Brooklyn, New York,
welcome. Big up from Jamaica. Welcome.
Good to see you here [laughter]
as well. Um, yes. And Vancouver Island,
that's Jody. Good to see you here
always. Happy to see all of you here uh
today on this Sabbath. So, we are a
little behind because we we started
late, but we are happy to be here and
glad that our technical difficulties
have been resolved and so we can move
forward. Um, I think we should go into
the t-shirt message because we're late.
>> So, the message is trust like Ruth,
protect like Rahab, lead like Deborah,
pray like Hannah, fight like Esther,
rejoice like Mary. Okay, that yes, this
did mention a lot of the women in the
Bible, but this what I'm about to say
goes for men and women. Um, first of
all, a lot of times we and I will start
off with the women. A lot of times, um,
as women, we do so much for for for
family and for others. And that's great.
And we're supposed to, God has put us on
this earth to to be a helpmate to our
husbands, to be mothers to our children,
to be great daughters and sisters and
all the things that we do. Um employees,
we're employees for for people. And so,
um, we do all of these things. And these
are amazing women in the Bible that this
t-shirt is listing. But it's so very
important for you still to pour into
yourself so that you can show up uh set
boundaries that you can show up to to be
the best wife and make sure you take
time for yourself. And that's important
because as women um we don't do that as
much as we should. Uh a lot of times we
just turn into not just women but superw
women and then we're like you know not
we not like we're trying to be like the
cartoon superwoman. Or was Superwoman
like a real? Anyway, so a real show or
was it cartoon? I can't remember. I
think it was both.
>> Okay. So, we don't mentally say, "Oh, I
want to be Superwoman." But we
automatically just go into superwoman
gear. And we can see here again from the
shirt that there were amazing women in
the Bible. And God used amazing uh they
used women to do amazing things to bring
forth whatever his will was and men
obviously. Um but we want to take
example from them that we can be used by
God to do amazing things. Uh but we also
want to he has put us on this earth like
what I just said to be mothers, wives,
daughters, sisters, employees, all of
that. But we have to pour into oursel
first so that
>> employers
>> employers and employees. Yeah,
employers. What am I saying? Of course,
employers. Employers and employees. So
we have to pour into ourselves so that
we can show up and be the best version
of whatever we're doing to who to
whoever we're being our amazing self to.
we have to pour into ourselves first and
a lot of times as women we forget to
pour into ourselves and we just think
like give give especially to our
children um but we need to learn how to
set boundaries so that we'll be the best
moms and the best wives and etc all
those things. So yeah we can take we can
see great examples from women in the
Bible um but we can and we can learn
from them but also learning how to put
boundaries down is very very important.
>> Amen. That's the message for today.
>> Amen. Amen.
Uh
I always like to say that you know sin
came into the Bible or into existence
>> through a woman.
>> But God will use a woman
>> to put an end to sin at the end of time.
>> Yeah.
>> When he says the Bible says the God of
peace shall bruise Satan under your feet
shortly.
>> Right. He's talking about the church
>> and the church is symbolized as a woman,
>> right?
>> Um and so, uh a woman is going to defeat
Satan.
>> Yes. Amen.
>> Through the power of Jesus. Amen.
>> Yes. Amen. Amen.
>> So, um I think we're going to, as I
said, we're kind of like behind a little
bit. So,
>> we are behind. So, we're going to jump
in.
>> We're going to jump in the the uh the
question and answer session. We're going
to pray.
>> Yes. Uh, and then, uh, you're taking
>> I'm taking mental health questions and
you're taking Bible questions. And you
can put mental health questions in the
chat. I have a few from last week that I
have, but you can also put in the chat
mental health questions. I would say
Bible questions, but I think you have
quite a few. Maybe you've covered some
of those that are on your list.
>> Yeah.
>> Because it's a list that builds. But
>> yeah.
>> Yeah. And please comment in the chat
when you're hearing the answer and all
of those things. Yeah,
>> you are part of this program with us.
>> And I have to say this, we have a great
group of women in Orlando right now that
are LMOC members of our church. You know
them very well. Um, uh, sister, sister
Amra, uh, Sister Denise, uh, Sister
Jacqueline, [clears throat] and, uh,
Sister Shaine are all at GYC and, uh,
they will be leading, they will be
praying for the church and for you and
for all of us over your requests live
from Orlando today. [clears throat] But,
um, they get to be together, which is
great.
>> Yeah.
>> So, this is great. So, I'm happy for
them.
>> Okay. Um, let's pray and then uh, I'll
take the first question.
>> Yes. All right, please.
>> Heavenly Father, we thank you Lord for
uh your goodness and grace towards us.
Lord, I pray today that you would guide
us um as we answer these questions from
the Bible. Lord, please uh speak through
us, Lord. And um we just thank you uh
for again your love towards us. Bless
this service. We pray in Jesus name.
Amen.
>> Amen.
>> All right. Um, so I am going to start
with a question that uh was asked and it
this one might be um a long answer but
I'm just going to try to uh juice this
question down if you will and it's a
pretty significant question. So
in uh the question is Adventists teach
that Christ entered the most holy place
in 1844 according to Daniel 8:14
but Hebrews says he entered once for all
into the heavenly sanctuary. Hebrews 9
11 and 12. How do we reconcile these two
passages without undermining either the
cross or the investigative judgment?
Um [clears throat]
so
uh I've done a whole study on this
particular question
>> and um this can really take a lot of
time uh because it requires an
understanding of the entire book of
Hebrews.
So I think what a lot of um a lot of
uh skeptics of of Adventism particularly
when it comes to to to Daniel uh to 1844
and Daniel 8:14 and our belief that
Jesus uh when he ascended into heaven
did not immediately begin his most holy
place ministry. uh people will use the
book of Hebrews
to attempt to teach that Christ entered
the most holy place upon his ascension.
>> However, if you do a chapter by chapter
study on the book of Hebrews,
>> you will see that
um
the book of Hebrews teaches no such
thing.
the entire purpose of the book of
Hebrews. Paul is writing the book of
Hebrews and most scholars believe that
the book of Hebrews was written
uh just
before
uh 70 AD.
>> Okay. So 70 AD is when the temple is
destroyed.
That's not coincidental.
Paul is writing
at a time when he when the temple is
still standing but about to be
destroyed.
Paul's argument in the book of Hebrews
as he's writing to his own people, it is
to the Hebrews.
His argument is not about
whether Jesus has entered into the holy
place in the heavenly sanctuary or the
most holy place in the heavenly
sanctuary. That's not the argument.
That's not what the people were um
debating in his day. Right? The thing
that Paul was trying to get across was
that there was a true tabernacle in
heaven where Jesus is now ministering.
That was the big deal. That was the
argument. And a lot of people um kind of
read
read a current issue back into an
ancient text as if the people in Jesus's
day in Paul's day were arguing over,
hey, did Jesus enter the holy place in
heaven or did he enter the most holy
place in heaven?
as if Paul was writing
to say, "Hey, those Adventists in the
future who are going to say that Jesus
entered the holy place, not the most
holy place, I'm writing to to refute
that error." He's not writing any such
thing.
The whole purpose of the book of Hebrews
is to demonstrate
that
Jesus is in the true tabernacle.
That is the one that we're supposed to
be focused on,
not this earthly temple, which I believe
Paul knew was about to be destroyed in
just a few years.
>> Okay? So if I can say it this way, the
book of Hebrews
does not address at all what compartment
Jesus or what ministry
um Jesus entered into in the sanctuary.
The entire argument is that there is a
heavenly tabernacle and Jesus is in that
heavenly tabernacle now and the present
tabernacle is about to pass away.
So when we understand that we will not
read into the book of Hebrews, oh well
the Bible says he entered into the most
holy place. No, the book of Hebrews
doesn't say that at all.
>> The book of Hebrews uses the day of
atonement analogy
which again kind of throws people off.
>> And and here's what I mean by that. So
again, there are 13 chapters in the book
of Hebrews. Mhm.
>> Seven of those chapters, Hebrews 1-7,
don't deal with with the sanctuary, holy
place versus most most holy place at
all. Mhm.
>> When you get to Hebrews chapter 8 and
Hebrews chapter 9 and Hebrews chapter
10,
>> the entire purpose of those three
chapters
is basically showing that listen, you
know how the the high priest was the
only one that could enter into the most
holy place
>> uh in the yearly services. Mhm.
>> In the same way,
Jesus is the only priest that has
entered into the heavenly temple.
>> He's not saying Jesus is the only one
that has entered into the most holy
place in the heavenly temple as if there
are other priests that are in the in the
heavenly temple that but can only go
into the holy place. Does that make
sense? Mhm.
>> His argument is
just as the high priest in the yearly
services is the only one that had access
to the presence of God. So Jesus out of
all the human priests that have ever
lived.
>> Jesus is the only one that has entered
in through the veil. And Hebrews
literally says that that veil
>> is his flesh.
>> Not the veil from the holy place to the
most holy place, but the veil which is
his flesh. Meaning through his death,
he's the only living he's the only
priest that is now living and alive in
the very presence of God.
>> There is no reference to well, is it the
holy place or the most holy place?
Because that's not what's on Paul's
mind.
>> What's on Paul's mind is
he is in the heavenly sanctuary.
>> Right?
>> So the book of Hebrews neither confirms
nor denies. It does not address
the question of what compartment
>> did Jesus begin his ministry in. Mhm.
>> Okay. So,
pretty again it's an indepth
>> um
>> question right
>> which would require an understanding of
the entire book of Hebrews,
>> right?
>> But we've juiced it down so that you
understand the book of Hebrews
>> does not address Jesus entering holy
place versus most holy place.
>> The whole purpose is
>> there is a heavenly temple and Jesus is
in that temple.
Amen.
>> And just to answer this very quickly, is
photo theology GPT because I just saw
that as well. Is photo theology GPT
started by SDAs or is it
non-denominational? So, um the
photoology GPT is uh I I'm the one that
actually started that. uh it is my
system of Bible study
>> and uh it is basically teaching people
how to study the Bible without telling
you exactly what to believe. Right? So
photo theology is equipping you with the
tools to rightly divide the word of God.
>> All right. So two questions down for me.
>> Amen.
>> To you.
>> Okay. Um
All right. Um,
I should have brought my glasses in.
>> Okay. No, it's okay. I have
>> Go ahead. Go ahead. Go ahead.
>> So, um, so Robert asked, "Are you saying
that Christ is not in the most holy
place now?" No, Christ is in the most
holy place now. Um,
Christ is doing his most holy place
ministry
now.
Uh what I'm saying is that when the book
of Hebrews was written, the purpose was
not to argue to the Jews, hey Jesus is
in the holy place, is in the most holy
place, not the holy place. That wasn't
even their argument.
>> The Jews were like, we don't believe
there's a heavenly temple. We don't
believe that Jesus is in it.
>> The tabernacle is here on earth. So that
was the context of Paul's writing the
book of Hebrews was to convince them of
a heavenly tabernacle in which Jesus
>> was presently dwelling. He does not
address holy place or most holy place in
terms of here's where Jesus is.
>> Okay.
>> All right.
>> Go ahead.
>> Okay. So this is a question. This is a
good question. says, "How can we tell
the difference between setting healthy
boundaries in relationship in
relationshipships
and just shutting people out?" Very good
question. Very good question because it
is a fine line at times to know the
difference. Um so not knowing your exact
situation um but there are many
situations where people have been abused
or hurt or whatever the situation is.
And so they're wanting to put a boundary
to say, you know what, I'm not gonna
allow myself to be exposed to this. I
will basically love you from afar. I
will pray for you. All of these things,
but I'm going to put boundaries down
because um you know, I don't if I if the
boundaries get diffused or get blurred
or whatever, this is going to cause me
more harm than good. Right? So that's
one case uh scenario. Then there's
another situation where um you're
wanting to put boundaries uh down um but
you don't know exactly how to do that.
Usually this is more difficult with a
family member because maybe even a
mother, a father, a sibling. Um, and I
like to say because a lot of times it's
not that people don't know how to put a
boundary down or that that's a blurred
thing, but because your relationship is
so close, say, with a mother or a father
or a sibling, um, and you just don't you
don't want to come off to seem like
you're being mean. So, I mean, you can
even say like you I always think
communication is the best thing. I
always like think that communication is
the best thing. So, it's it's great to
like if you're in that type of needing
to put a boundary down and it's with
like a parent or a good or a sibling or
somebody that's very close to you um or
has been in the past but has grown
distant because of whatever the
situation is and you're needing to s put
a boundary down. So, at times in that
type of situation you may need to have a
conversation. You may have to in a very
mature, loving,
Christc centered way have this type of
conversation with somebody that you're
needing to put the boundary down that
you've been very close to and you know
to let them know to say look I will
always care for you, love you, all of
these things. Um, but
you know I've been hurt here and this is
how I feel when this happens and I just
think we I'm going to not I think but
I'm going to set this boundary down. um
in our relationship. Not you're not like
um shutting them out altogether. You're
just putting a boundary like you can
maybe still have some contact with them
because I mean it depends on every
situation is different. But having a
conversation and maybe even in that
conversation they will really begin to
see what how badly you've been hurt and
things will things can change and maybe
no boundary will be needed but when a
boundary you feel a boundary is needed
um even if it's somebody that you have
been very close to and it's and I I feel
like people have harder times when it is
those closer relationships again like
parents and siblings um and and and
other situations that you can have that
very loving conversation and just
letting them know in a loving way what
you are doing whatever that boundary
looks like for you because every's bound
everybody's boundary looks a little bit
different. So I hope that helps. All
right.
Um
next question we're going to address is
uh about the Exodus as a typological
architecture. So here's a question.
Given that the Exodus serves as a
typical as a top typological
architecture for the end times, does the
recurrence of the song of Moses in
Revelation 15 confirm that Pharaoh's
irrational pursuit into the sea was not
merely a military blunder, but the
archetypal manifestation of the
overmastering delusion destined to
consume the armies of the Antichrist?
That's a long question. Mhm.
>> Um and basically the the gist of the
question is this and it's a very good
connection as well.
Um the in the Exodus story,
the song of Moses is sung after the
children of Israel cross the Red Sea and
Pharaoh's armies are destroyed. Um,
so
they uh
the the song the
song of Moses sung in Revelation chapter
is paralleling
or is revealing that the same thing that
happened with the Exodus will happen
again. God's people, the second Moses,
the heavenly Moses, Jesus, is going to
come to earth. He's going to lead his
people across a parted sky and they're
going to stand on Mount Zion singing
that song of Moses,
which doesn't prove,
but it strongly suggests that just as
Pharaoh's armies
marched into
march into the sea thinking we're going
to get these people.
That same type of delusion
is what will be exercised not only by
Satan but also the people that are
deceived by him.
Right? That strong delusion, that
overmastering delusion that um we can we
can beat Jesus. Mhm.
>> Um,
and it's kind of a a a scary thought to
think of
>> how deluded one must be to think that
they can beat God.
>> Uh, to think that they can fight against
God. And this becomes especially true at
the end of the millennium when the the
armies of Gog and Magog representing the
entire wicked world
will actually try to defeat the new
Jerusalem as it's coming down out of
heaven.
>> Um
when the spirit of God is totally
removed, strong delusion is the end
result.
So while the song of Moses in Revelation
15 doesn't doesn't say oh the people
will be strongly deluded it the strong
correlation is just as Pharaoh and his
armies were deluded so Satan and his
armies will be deluded at the end of
time.
>> Yeah. Um do you want me to take another
question or
>> you can I have Yeah, you can. And you
can put your mental health questions in
the chat. I have a few more, but you
have more Bible questions.
>> So, if you have them, you can put them
in the chat.
>> So, this question, I think I just
decided this morning that I'm actually
going to be preaching. I think I'm going
to preach on this next week.
>> Um, so I'm not going to answer the
question in full, but
uh part of the question is this. Well, I
I'll give you the full question, then
I'm tell you what I'm going to save till
next week. [clears throat]
>> Um,
so here it is. Is the doctrine of
original sin biblical? That's question
number one. And then part two is,
>> is there any credibility to last
generation theology?
>> So, okay. Okay. You're going to explain
all what those terms even mean? Okay.
Because not everybody will.
>> Yeah. So, the idea of original sin is
that uh human beings are born guilty of
the sin of Adam. And uh basically that
we're born with uh with there's no good
in us, no redeeming value in us. It's
just we're just purely
>> depraved and we we are guilty of Adam's
sin.
So the Bible does not teach that we are
guilty of Adam sin. The Bible actually
says that
um because of Adam, death passed upon
all men,
>> right? Death passed upon all men.
Meaning we all die because we all die
because when Adam sinned, he brought
death into the world.
>> We are not punished for Adam's sin.
Right? So, the Bible tells us that um
uh let's see,
give me one second here.
>> Okay. So, I'm going to come back to the
I'm going come back to to Fred's
question here in a moment.
>> Okay.
>> Um so,
>> we are not punished because of somebody
else's sin, right? The sins of the
father
>> uh the sins of the father will not be
attributed to the son. The sins of the
son will not be attributed to the
father. The bible says the soul that
sinnth it shall die.
>> We die because of you know we are guilty
because of our own sins not because of
someone else's sin.
>> So the question of original sin we we
are born with a fallen nature but that
is not the same thing as being guilty of
Adam's sin.
Okay. So that's question number one. Um,
question number two,
uh, talking about the last generation
theology
>> is a question about perfection.
And does the last generation
have to meet a certain standard of
perfection, call perfection, and why is
that different from other generations
before that last generation? I'm not
going to answer that question. I think I
think I'm gonna preach on that next week
because it's a pretty relevant
>> okay
>> topic and one that needs to be
importantly I mean needs to be
understood
>> and taken the time
>> so I'm going to jump
>> so tune in next week yeah
>> for that answer
>> last generation theology I'll be
speaking on next week
>> all right
>> um
>> let me come back to this um
>> different.
>> Yeah.
So
what we need to understand is that in
the heavenly sanctuary right
>> there is no there is no like separation
in terms of architecture like I think a
lot of times we think architecture
uh is Jesus in the presence of God now
or not? Is he at the right hand of the
father now or not? When Jesus is in
heaven, he's at the right hand of the
father regardless,
>> right?
>> Yeah, that makes sense.
>> When you can find many places in the Old
Testament sanctuary where the priest is
in the outer court and he's in the
presence of God,
>> he's described as before the presence of
the Lord. Um, Nahab and Nah, Naab and
Abaiu are destroyed before the presence
of the Lord. People are in the in the
priests in the in the holy place. They
were before the presence of the Lord.
Mhm.
>> Jesus in heaven
>> is already in the presence of God.
>> That's number one.
>> So, so don't think, oh, Jesus was not in
the presence of God for this amount of
time in heaven, but then in 1844 he came
into the presence of God. That's not
what we're saying. Um secondly
and the reason for that is that Jesus
doesn't c have sin like uh the you know
earthly priests who couldn't enter into
his presence had a veil covering because
they couldn't enter into his presence
because of their sin.
>> There is no there is no Jesus can't
enter into the presence of his father
because of sin. Right.
>> Right.
If you are in heaven,
>> you are in the presence of God
regardless
of you're in the sanctuary or outside
the sanctuary. Angels are in the
presence of God. Period.
>> That one principle makes so much sense.
Like Jesus didn't have
personal sin
>> like from himself. Like he didn't need
to be
>> Yeah. like veiled from the presence of
God.
>> No.
>> Right.
>> And the fact that he's also
>> Yeah. So when the Bible says he's at the
right hand of God, at the right hand of
power,
>> it's not it's not speaking locationally
>> as if if he's ministering
>> doing most holy place things, that means
that he's not in the presence of God.
>> It's not saying that at all. And and
that's not what it means. Regardless of
where Jesus is in the in the sanctuary,
he is in the presence of God. Okay.
Secondly,
um
when when we
>> go to for example the book of Revelation
chapter
one,
Jesus is seen standing in the midst of
seven
>> golden candlesticks.
Where are the seven golden candlesticks
located
>> on the outer
>> there? It's located in the holy place.
>> Right.
>> To say that Jesus
is not in the holy place or he didn't go
to the holy place. He skipped that.
>> Is
literally denying Revelation chapter
one, right? M
>> Jesus standing in the in the midst of
the seven golden candlesticks.
>> And and there's what I what what I would
say about this, right? Because a lot of
times people, well, what about Ellen
White? What about Ellen White? We don't
go to Ellen White to prove anything,
>> right? we go to the Bible and we stay
right there in the Bible and we're going
to prove from the Bible, hey, this is
why we believe Jesus
as he's following the patterns of
pattern of the Old Testament uh
sanctuary which he instituted.
There was a holy place ministry
>> and then a most holy place ministry. So
if you were to look at the whole
structure of the book of revelation,
you've got the seven seals, you got the
seven churches, you have the seven
trumpets. All of those things are
unfolding within the context of the most
holy place,
>> right? There is the seven churches and
the opening vision is Jesus standing at
the seven
um the the the seven lampstands, the the
golden candlestick. That's the holy
place. You go to the to the seven seals,
the opening vision is the table of
showbread. And the reason that we know
that is it is is because it is the
article of furniture
that was found directly across from the
seven branch candlestick. And again, the
opening vision of the seven seals
literally mentions the seven branch
candlestick. And across from it was this
throne.
that throne.
>> The only thing in the Old Testament that
was across from the candlestick is table
of showbread. The table of showbread was
located on the sides of the north. And
when you go to Psalm 48, you see that
the sides of the north is a symbol of
God's throne, God's city, God's
rulership.
>> When you get to the seven trumpets, the
beginning vision of the seven trumpets
is the altar of incense.
That's the very first that's the first
entire first half of the book of
revelation
>> is unfolding within the context of the
holy place
>> right
>> it is not until we get to revelation 11
17 18 and 19
>> that John says I saw the most holy place
open and from revelation 11 onward it's
all most holy place
>> incidentally that's where you have the
preaching of the three angels messages
>> that's where you have revelation chapter
14 I saw another angel fly in the midst
of heaven having everlasting gospel to
preach unto them that dwell on the
earth. That's where you have all these
things unfolding,
>> right?
>> After John sees the most holy place
opening up.
>> So [clears throat]
again,
you know, it's it is uh
it doesn't take a lot of
brain power,
>> right? Mhm.
>> to just be like, "Oh, Jesus,
>> if he's in the presence of God, then
that must mean that that he's in the
most holy place." That is not a biblical
>> you you you can't show that from the Old
Testament type,
>> right?
>> You can't show that from the New
Testament.
>> Anybody in any angel in heaven is in the
presence of God of God. Heaven is in the
presence of God.
>> Heaven is the presence of God.
>> Yeah. So to say, well, if he was in a if
he was doing a a holy place ministry,
ministering at the candlestick,
ministering at the altar of incense,
ministering at the table of showbread,
that means you're saying that he wasn't
in the presence of God. This is a false
teaching.
>> You know, you're it's it's a cliche
thing to just say it's a false teaching.
Why? Because what?
>> Because
everyone else says it's a false
teaching, so it must be.
So anyway, I will leave that question
and for those of you that still are
like, you know, hey, I want to
understand more about this, like
>> go study it out deeper for yourself.
>> But you got to study it using correct
principles. You can't just make stuff up
and be like if you were in the holy
place and that means you weren't in the
presence of God. go look up whatever
high priest was in the holy place and
see if they didn't have to go in with
absolute protection because
>> they were in the presence of
>> God whether they were in the holy place
or the most holy place.
>> Okay.
>> I don't know what group of think or what
uh well I want to say what group of
thinking teaches that. I don't know what
>> like like why would they want to prove
that Jesus is not in the presence of
God? So in essence, the way to the way
to like say that 1844 is wrong,
>> that a judgment has begun is wrong
>> is to say, well, the judgment happened
at the cross.
>> Okay, got it.
>> Right.
>> Um, let me I'll share one more point and
then looks like Sabbath school is about
this then.
>> Well, that's almost
>> almost.
>> Um,
>> I have a next question that will like
take our minds completely to a new
direction, but go ahead.
>> So,
what what people say when when they're,
you know, pointing to, oh, Jesus entered
the most holy place. What they're saying
is in essence that the day of atonement
was fulfilled at the cross.
>> That's what they're saying.
>> That the day of atonement is the is the
day that the high priest entered into
the most holy place and this was
fulfilled at the cross.
But there is a problem with this. Um,
and uh, Renee, I see your question about
a a veil in the heavenly sanctuary. I
I'll come to that in a moment.
>> Um,
so here's a problem. The Day of
Atonement is not the only feast of the
Jewish year.
>> There was the Passover. There was the
feast of unleavened bread. There was the
feast of first fruits. There was the
feast of Pentecost.
>> Um there's the feast of trumpets, the
day of atonement, and then finally the
um feast of tabernacles. Okay?
>> And these feasts had order to them. So
Passover is the first feast.
>> One day after that is unleaven bread.
One day after that is the feast of first
fruits. 50 days later is the feast of is
the feast of Pentecost.
>> Then you had about a three-month period
where nothing is going on. No yearly
feast. And then you have the feast of
trumpets. 10 days later the day of
atonement. And then finally a few days
after that the the feast of tabernacles.
Mhm.
>> Here is the problem, you guys, with
Jesus entering into the most holy place
uh on the day of atonement, which would
be at his death, burial, and
resurrection.
>> Here's the problem.
We know that
all the feasts
were not fulfilled at the death of
Jesus.
>> The death of Jesus did not fulfill all
the feasts.
There is no
way around this.
So for example,
if I were to ask someone, hey, was was
Pentecost fulfilled? Or was Passover
fulfilled when Jesus died?
>> And they say yes. And I say, why?
Because Jesus, they say, I'd say, why?
They say Jesus is a Passover lamb. And
when he died, Passover was fulfilled.
>> What about unleavened bread? The feast
of unleven bread. M
>> it's representing Jesus in the ground.
Unleaven bread. Bread that has not
risen. Leaven causes things to unleaven
bread.
>> He was in the ground.
>> On the third day he rose. First fruits.
>> So here's a question.
Was the feast of first fruits fulfilled
when Jesus died?
>> And the answer is no.
>> The feast of first fruits could not have
been fulfilled until Jesus resurrected.
Meaning, yes, the Passover was fulfilled
at the death of Christ.
>> Unleaven bread was fulfilled at the
death of Christ, but Passover was I
mean, but first fruits was not fulfilled
at the death of Christ. It was fulfilled
at his resurrection.
>> What about Pentecost?
Was Pentecost fulfilled at the death of
Christ? And now you you're beginning to
see the answer is obviously no. When
Jesus died, Pentecost was not fulfilled.
It was only 50 days later after the
death of Jesus or after the resurrection
of Jesus was Pentecost fulfilled on the
day of Pentecost.
>> Okay. So if these first four feasts were
fulfilled but in a chronological order,
how do we then take the day of atonement
which is at the end of the year
>> and say, "Oh, that was fulfilled when
Jesus died or that was fulfilled when
Jesus went to heaven." You just took the
feast and just you follow the order of
Passover, unleven bread, first fruits,
Pentecost, but then you just totally
take a feast at the end of the year and
say, "Oh yeah, that one was done at the
cross.
There are three festivals that happen at
the end of the year. The feast of
trumpets, the day of atonement, and the
feast of tabernacles.
>> No Christian anywhere believes that the
feast of tabernacles will be fulfilled
until Jesus comes again and tabernacles
with his people. That's a common
understanding.
So if the feast of tabernacles is not
fulfilled till the very end of time and
the feast of trumpets which many
Christians not as Adventists we don't
believe this but many Christians believe
the feast of trumpets is when Jesus
comes again with a trumpet sound right
oh that'll be the feast of trumpets well
how are those two feasts the so the fall
festivals have three feasts trumpets day
of atonement tabernacles they will take
two of those feasts and say that's at
the end of time.
>> But the third of those feasts they say,
"Oh, that was at the cross."
>> Okay,
>> you're totally ripping the order
>> of this one feast and putting it in a
place that it doesn't belong.
>> Meaning it's confusion,
>> right?
So that is another aspect to look at
this from, right?
>> When you're when you're trying to, you
know, oh, the the um the the the Day of
Atonement was fulfilled at the cross.
Jesus went straight into the most holy
place.
>> You're you're literally you got to
destroy the entire Bible to hold on to
that kind of a thing. That kind of
thinking.
>> Okay.
>> Is there a veil in heaven that separates
Jesus from the F?
>> No.
>> There is no literal in Let me say it
this way.
There is no
there is no purpose for a veil
>> which would separate Jesus or anybody
from the presence of God. God is not
veiled
>> in
>> um in heaven
>> from anybody. Mhm.
>> So we may say symbolically speaking,
right? When we speak symbolically, you
know that that
>> when the book of Hebrews uses the term
within the veil, it is not using the
term to say that there's a veil that was
hiding Jesus from God in the heavenly
sanctuary.
>> It literally says the veil was his
flesh.
>> Right? So upon his death, burial, and
resurrection, through his death, burial,
and resurrection, he was able to stand
in the presence of God.
>> Okay. All right.
>> Okay.
>> I think that'll be enough on that.
>> Yeah. Go to your
>> There are some follow-up questions. I
told you that this next question would
take us from that to the very opposite
end of questions as far as topic goes.
This question is, is it fair to expect
someone to make extra efforts?
Oops. Okay, that's not the question.
Sorry, guys. Um,
okay, here it goes. Sorry. How do we
honestly deal with sexual desires?
And is it really realistic to expect
people to wait until marriage in today's
world? Can't denying normal sexual
desires hinder our mental health? So I
told you it was like complete on a whole
another side. So okay. So yes, this
question is if you deny your sexual
desires, will the will this affect your
mental health? Um well, first of all,
the first part of the question is um
is it, you know, can we honestly
um realistically teach and expect people
to wait until marriage? Well, the Bible
says that, right? That is the confounds
that sex was produced was between Adam
and Eve to be fruitful and multiply. it
was um it was um couched if you will
within a marriage. Um and so when you
take it outside of the the marriage um
then it's then that's not healthy and
that can actually affect your mental
health because you're not in a covenant
relationship with a person um to be
experiencing these type of things. Now,
if you um if you decide or if you choose
to to abstain from um the sexual desires
because you're not married, will that
affect your mental health? No.
Now, if it does affect your mental
health, then that's saying that you're
either doing this in just your own um
what you would say your own grit, your
own strength, your own whatever. And
it's not coming from a love relationship
between you and God. Meaning like I love
God and my relationship with God is um
in such an intimate serious place that I
would never uh want to experience
something that's outside of God's will
for my life. So, it's your thought
system and your and the way you're
looking at it um that you're denying
yourself because um again, God made the
act of sex. Matter of fact, in Christian
uh confounds, we don't talk about sex
enough. And I say that to say in the way
that it's supposed to to be, we actually
shun it or make it make it seem like
it's so taboo. Like, let's not talk
about it even if we're talking about it
in a marriage because that's God created
that. He created that for a a mar for
the marriage and for a man and a woman
that are married to be able to do that
to procreate and for connection. I mean
it that's just the bottom line. It helps
to keep your marriage and to helps you
keep you connected. So I say all of that
to say it's his creation. So if it's his
creation, he tells us how to do it and
when we should do, you know, when and
what time in our life we should do it.
And that is when we are married and in a
covenant relationship through marriage.
Um and so that if we follow God's will
and anything that doesn't cause if we're
doing it correctly with the right with
the right thought process, that's not
going to cause a mental health issue or
it won't affect our mental health. Um
because it's just like any other
temptation. Um if you're not married
then yes you might you will have a
sexual desire or temptation but you're
not married. So just like so at that
time it is not God's will that you are
in sexual relationship with a person
because you're not married. So when God
is when it's when it's outside of God's
framework, then yes, you're going to be
if you're if you're wanting to
participate or if you do participate in
that outside of God's framework, that
will cause mental health. But if you're
in a committed intimate, and I say
intimate relationship like you and God
are so close that even almost like the
way Joseph was, I love to use this as an
example when he was tempted because he
was tempted uh by Piper's wife. He said,
"How could I do this sin against my
father?" That is the space we want to be
in. That we have such a close
relationship with God that even when
we're outside, we're not in a marriage.
We're not in a covenant relationship uh
marriage. And so that having sexual
relations is not God's will for us at
that time. Um but our relationship with
God is so close that even when that
temptation comes, it's just like, "Oh,
there's a temptation." But my love and
my intimacy with God is greater than
that temptation.
>> Yeah. You know, [clears throat] I think
it's important to understand as well
that
>> in the marriage relationship,
>> the the two become one.
>> And you actually give yourself to
another person. The way that God
designed is that when you're married,
the two become one flesh and you're
giving your a part of yourself to
another person.
>> So imagine doing that again and again
and again and again with a bunch of
different people.
>> Yeah.
>> Right. you're
>> that will damage your mental health.
>> Yeah. You're in a way giving away
yourself
>> so that
it's hard to kind of explain, but
>> the person you may end up marrying,
>> you weren't able to give your complete
your completed self to because you were
giving yourself away.
>> You were giving pieces away,
>> pieces of yourself away to to different
people. Right? So this is why I think
it's important that uh that we follow
that biblical counsel and
>> you know I will I will say this in a
>> you know kind of a funny way it's not
funny but it is funny at the same time
is
>> okay
>> when you know when my brother and I
first became Christian
and we just would curse all the time.
>> Oh wow. Wow. Tiger.
>> I didn't know Tiger I Hi, guys. Our cat
is in here. I didn't know Tiger was in
here. I heard him. I thought he was at
the door. Oh, he opened the door.
>> Yes.
>> All right.
>> He has been
three years.
>> I didn't know he was inside
>> trying to get to the garage and he just
uh to our studio and he just
>> he's done that during the week, but not
on a Sabbath program.
>> And now, how do we
>> So, Tiger, do you want
>> skillfully?
>> I know. Tiger, can we continue?
Okay, we're just gonna we're gonna keep
answering the question. Okay, I heard
him, but I thought he was at the door
crying to get in. He was actually in and
he actually
>> We don't know how he opened the door to
get in.
>> Yeah. Pray for Tiger. He's a lot. But
you love the cat. They love you, Tiger.
You you're you're you're you want a lot
of fame.
>> Yes. All right. So,
>> and you see where he is. He's trying to
get close to pastor because he loves the
pastor the most. He's not even trying to
get to me because he knows.
>> But you could just chew him off. All
right. He's He's not gonna listen.
>> Okay. All right. We're gonna just finish
with Tiger.
>> Yeah. Um, what was I talking about?
[laughter]
>> Totally.
>> You were talking about Oh, you and and
Sean used to
>> Yes. We would curse all the time.
>> And
so, you know, when we came into the
church, like we
no one brought us into the church like
we didn't go through an evangelistic
series or anything. So, it wasn't like
we had a series of studies. So anyway,
you know, we're we're doing our thing.
And I remember my brother coming to me
one day and being like, you know, man, I
think if we're really really really
really really going to be Christians, we
got to stop cursing.
>> And I remember I looked at my brother
like what? Like what are you even
talking about, man? How's that even
possible? Like
>> you know, I remember thinking in my
mind, who then shall be saved if we do
this?
>> And that's how you know what I'm saying?
Like back then it was just like that's a
huge thing. And I think in the same way
a lot of people,
you know, may initially think, wait,
what? No intimacy before marriage? What?
That just sounds crazy.
>> But when you're trying to follow the
will of God,
>> um,
>> we're letting him stay, guys. We're not
going to kick him off.
>> Your mind begins to see things
and understand things differently.
>> So,
>> yeah.
>> Yeah.
And I think and I'm going to say
hopefully this clarifies what I was
trying to say earlier too is that we
um God created sex for marriage and I
think that even as Christians in
marriage marriage situations we don't
even want to talk about it within the
marriage context because so when you put
a negative stigma or it has a negative
stigma on it because
>> outside of marriage marriage, it is not
God's will. Um, that carries over in the
Christian world into the marriage
conversation, too, which it shouldn't
be. So, when you get married, it's
almost I I don't know. It's not like you
have to be out here telling everybody
your marriage marital sexual business.
I'm not saying that. I'm just saying
that it just is kind of taboo. like you
just don't talk about um it's just not
talked about in a positive way in the
Christian circles
>> which just put more um in that sense I
think it's that's not healthy mental
health-wise. I mean, just because
especially when you're talking to young
people, you're already telling them
you're not married, so you need to not,
you know, you have to abstain from sex
or all these things because the Bible
says so. But it just sounds it just even
when you go into marriage in the
Christian realm, it just continues to
take on a negative, you just don't talk
about it in a positive sense. Yeah. I
think it should be spoken more, it needs
to be spoken more in a positive sense
within the marriage uh relationship.
Yeah. So, I think that's not healthy
either for Christians.
>> Okay.
>> Well, I guess uh
>> we have time for um a few more
questions.
>> Well, may as well do this one. Will
serpents be in the new earth?
>> Um and I guess the question is like
willp animals, you know, serpents.
>> Oh, yeah. Okay. Yeah.
>> Since tiger's here, uh you know, may as
well address the question.
Yeah. Um, so remember that uh serpents
were are were not when God created the
serpent, he wasn't creating an evil
creature, right?
>> So uh if the lion and the lamb and and
the wolf and you know these other
creatures will be in heaven um then
yeah I believe servants will be in
heaven and maybe they will look
different. Maybe they will not be
>> so uh cuz
>> yeah I mean
>> if you see a flying serpent
>> I don't want to see a serpent in heaven
>> but in heaven will be changed.
>> Well God did
>> and I would like we will like serpents
then right
>> but I don't like them now.
>> If they're on the ground they're I think
they're evil if they fly that they're
they're good. Right. That's how God
originated the serpent.
>> Yeah.
>> I don't know.
>> You don't want to you're afraid it's
going to be Satan. Satan's not going to
be
>> No.
>> He's not going to be in heaven. So you
can like the serpent. Okay, you're being
funny.
>> I'm just I'm just saying I don't like
snakes
>> anyway. They will like snakes.
>> Yeah, they will probably be in heaven.
They will be
>> but you won't have fear,
>> but you won't have fear of of serpents
or any creatures
>> because God doesn't give us a spirit of
fear. Now I feel that way about
Okay, don't judge me. Lions and tigers
and like do I really [laughter]
those like I was like wow. But I guess
they're they're not going to be
>> they're not going to want to attack us,
kill us. So we don't have the spirit of
fear. Our fears will not be in heaven.
>> Yeah.
>> Um there is another question. You said
we have time for for one more. Two more.
>> You have time for one more. And I could
have time for one more.
>> Yeah. And this one is just uh just too
long of a question, but I'll do this. Um
if the great controversy began with
questions about God's character, why
does scripture say sin will not rise a
second time
>> when free will still exists in the new
earth? What guarantees eternal loyalty
without removing freedom?
So um I think the simple answer to this
question is
um
the pain and suffering
that we experience in this world in this
life
um will
will be the the thing
the reminder we never want to experience
that again.
>> Right? Uh the wounds in Jesus's hands
that when we look at those wounds and
see, hey, this is what sin caused.
Remember that.
>> Um this is what guarantees sin will not
rise a second time.
>> Right?
>> It's not that God takes away our free
will. Mhm.
>> It's
it's the understanding of what sin did,
>> the the damage it caused, the loss it
caused. Um,
no one will say, "Hey, um, why don't we
revisit that?"
>> Right?
So um simp I think that's a simp the
simplest answer I can give is that
the the the nightmare of sin in this
world.
>> Um what it caused the damage the
destruction
will keep us from ever sinning again in
heaven.
>> Yeah.
>> Amen. Amen. All right. Well we still
have like three more minutes. So, I'm
going to
to answer the next question.
This is a good question, I think, to
close off. When someone in the church is
struggling emotionally,
what's the most helpful way we can show
up for them beyond just saying, "We'll
pray for you." And I I think and and
man, there's so much to even this. This
is a great question, actually, because
in the church setting and as Christians,
we say that be like, "Oh, I'll pray for
you." Number one, do we really?
Honestly, um I have to say like once I
started keeping my prayer journal, that
made it easier for me because I had a
section for others. I just put others,
meaning like these weren't my personal
prayers for myself or my for my family,
but others. And so that way when I would
see the person again, I would know that
okay, I have actually prayed because so
many times we say that and we don't
actually I mean it's a nice thing to say
in the moment but the best thing to do
is to really do it and that we're all we
I know I've been guilty of saying it but
not actually doing it um for whatever
reasons just you forget or whatever you
mean your heart is with them like
whatever they're going through but you
said you're going to pray you have to
actually be praying. Okay, that's one.
Um but you but the question is besides
just saying that or doing that. So I
think it's important to I mean we're
individuals church members are not
mental health therapists. So they're not
trained to be able to to give like
professional emotional mental health
care but you know having true empathy
learning that person spending time with
them getting to know them better. That's
how you're going to know for that
individual person how you can show up
for them in the best way that they need.
Mhm.
>> So really having real relationships in
the church. And I know we're an online
church, but I can say we have some real
relationships going on here. We we cry
together. We rejoice together. We know
each other. We know each other's prayer
requests, the burdens. We know like soon
as something's happening in somebody's
life, like that prayer chat that's on
that um [clears throat] on WhatsApp or
whatever that's like, hey, if you have a
prayer request and all of that stuff
that just are we're putting things in
there, like we know what's going on with
each other. that thing is always
running. Um, so and we get to know each
other in different settings to be able
to know this is what's going on in so-
and so's life. So you become you to
build a closer relationship with someone
is the only way that you're going to
really know how to be there for them and
what they um are needing. So there's no
one set thing for everybody. The only
one set thing is to get have a close um
relationship where you can have true
empathy because you really know them.
You can feel their hurt and their pain
for whatever they're going through, you
become real friends and real friends are
there for each other. So instead of just
being passing members in a church lobby
or in the hallway or just seeing each
other and just say, "Oh, happy Sabbath."
But you keep walking. So the same thing
here with our online church is just
saying happy Sabbath in the chat or
whatever or just knowing somebody's
name. Like really that's what Mighty
Networks is for to really get to know
each other better. The small groups you
get to know each other even better. And
then we have our WhatsApp thing. I mean
you know those are fun times together
but just spending time with a person is
the way that you're going to get to know
them in a more deeper intimate way so
that you can really know what they are
needing from you. So you're providing
what they need, not with just what you
think they need or just the basic, "Oh,
happy Sabbath. I'll pray for you."
>> So there's more. Just like any other
relationship, you need to have a deeper
relationship.
>> Yeah.
>> With those that you call sister and
brother,
you know. So anyways,
>> uh I think we'll end here.
>> Yeah, we can. And the timing is is is
good for us to end there. Just know that
you can always continue to put in
questions, Bible questions for the
pastor, mental health questions for me.
>> And we did have more questions, you
know, some questions that that
>> they were not answered. Yeah. So, well,
they'll be answered at the next the next
question and answer Sabbath school uh
next week. We'll be back with the
Christian Art of War. So, you're not
going to want to miss that. Gave our
Sabbath school panel a little bit of a
break. Um but we're looking forward to
getting back and jumping into that as
well. So
>> talk about your sermon.
>> Absolutely. Uh so the message that I'm
going to be sharing today
um is uh really
uh kept me up kept me up yesterday last
night. Um
it is going to be uh really really
significant really I think eyeopening.
Amen.
>> Um, a revelation and you know, we're be
beginning a new year. This message today
is going to be
kind of like a recap of of who we are,
where we are,
>> what's coming ne next, and how we
prepare for it.
So,
um,
and I know I typically say it's not what
you think, but this time y'all, it
really, really, really isn't. It's like
it's really not what you think. And once
you see it, you can't unsee it. Um, so
it's going to be beautiful. Make sure
you share the link. Make sure you let
people know, uh, divine service is
starting.
>> Yes. And uh you're not g listen and
you're not probably not gonna want to
miss this like let me come in 10 minutes
into the sermon. You probably want to be
there from the very beginning.
>> You want to be there. Yeah.
>> Because it builds.
>> So make sure make sure.
>> Yes. Yes. Continue to worship with us
like he said. Share like um this link
and also subscribe. So you want to share
like and subscribe. Uh so definitely
just invite someone to church and they
will by God's um by God's grace will be
very very blessed. So we're excited.
Continue to worship with us. We look
forward to seeing you in the divine
worship service.
The Lord also will be a refuge for the
oppressed, a refuge in times of trouble.
And they that know thy name will put
their trust in thee. For thou, Lord has
not forsaken them that seek thee.
In a world full of injustice, sorrow,
and pain, God is a place of refuge and
peace for his people. A salvation asylum
for the guilty and the oppressed. Puh
Honua is one of them.
Erected on the black lava flats, the Ka
coast of the Big Island, Pu Honua served
as a sanctuary of refuge [music] in
ancient times. Surrounded by the blue
waters of the Pacific Ocean on the
northwest [music] and a solid lava wall
in the southeast, this Hawaiian haven
served as a natural fortification.
It was an ideal place for the Ali, the
Hawaiian royalty [music] to establish
their residential and ceremonial sites.
Considered as royal sacred ground, it is
here that many of the ancient chiefs
[music] of Hawaii were buried. The last
of which was one of the sons of Kamehaha
the first in the year 1818. It is here
at the Kave Hao that the ancient priests
of Hawaii offered their sacrifices
[music] for centuries until the final
overthrow of the Kapu system by
Kamehameha II in 1819.
Littered with tall, swaying coconut
trees, clear and cool ocean waters,
fishing ponds, friendly [music] turtles,
black lava rocks, and a white sandy
shore, this place of refuge is just as
[music] beautiful as it is safe.
Now, there are many of these places of
refuge scattered [music] all throughout
the islands, but this is the last
authentic one that has been preserved,
containing some [music] ancient ruins
that date back to the 1400s. This island
shelter was a place of [music]
protection for wounded warriors as well
as displaced civilians during times of
war and battle. No physical harm could
be done to those [music] who reached the
boundaries of this place of refuge. All
within the walls were guaranteed the
protection of the king.
Modeled after the cities of refuge in
biblical times, it also offered [music]
protection from the avenger of blood. If
someone was guilty of breaking kapu or
sacred law, they would surely be put to
death. However, if the offender was able
to make it within the walls of Puh
Honua, they were protected from the
avenger. Though many were guilty and
deserved to die, here at Puh Honua, they
found a sanctuary of forgiveness and a
second chance [music] at life.
This sacred ancient Hawaiian site was
literally a sanctuary of forgiveness.
And in ancient biblical times, it was at
the time of the death of the high priest
that the forgiven offender was able to
leave and go home free in the power of
forgiveness.
This ancient Hawaiian history that
mirrors so closely the ancient
institutions of the Holy Bible. It tells
me that the true God of heavens was
communicating with our Hawaiian
ancestors. He was revealing to them his
holy ways of justice and mercy, grace
and peace.
For this [music] place of refuge is a
reflection of the wonderful plan of
salvation.
You see, each and every one of us are
guilty of breaking the [music] sacred
commands of God. We have violated the
perfect precepts of Jehovah. We have
trampled upon the holy law of love. And
because [music] of the foolishness of
our sinful choices, death is the only
just reward we deserve. Satan is free to
take us with him to destruction. But God
has not left us to ourselves. He has
provided a [music] place of refuge, a
heavenly pu honua. And if we flee to the
shelter of his grace, we will then find
the peace of pardon for all our
offenses. And because of the death of
our heavenly high priest, [music] Jesus
Christ, we can go back to our heavenly
home, free in forgiveness and liberated
in love. For there is no condemnation to
those who [music] are in Christ Jesus.
He took our punishment that we might
have his peace. This was the reality
that God was trying to teach our ancient
Hawaiian ancestors. And it [music] is
the same reality he desires for us to
experience today.
Is your life consumed [music] with
spiritual confusion?
Are you burdened with the guilt of sin?
Maybe you're running from your troubles,
[music] but you feel like you have no
place to hide and no place to rest.
Well, if so, I urge you to [music] run
to the heavenly puh honua. Do not delay.
You must go at once. For the adversary
of the devil, is [music] coming after
you like a roaring lion, seeking to
devour you in deception, distraction,
[music] and despair. Go at once to the
perfect place of refuge, where the enemy
has no power. Do not allow anything or
[music] anyone to hold you back. For it
is there that Jesus invites you to
surrender your sins to him, that you
might receive [music] mercy, grace, and
forgiveness, and life ever more. And
there you will dwell in the place of
safety, security, satisfaction, and
salvation in the true paradise of God.
We hope you've [music] been blessed and
inspired by this new Reflections of Hope
episode. This episode is one of many
that's been produced all over the world.
If you haven't done [music] so yet,
please give our video a like, share it
with your friends, and please follow us
on Instagram, Facebook, and YouTube. If
you'd like to see more inspiring [music]
episodes and get access to much more
uplifting content, please go now to
patreon.com/revelationof
hope and sign up to be a member of our
Patreon page. Your monthly support will
not only give you early [music] access
to many more inspiring videos, but it
will also enable us to continue to
produce more of these [music] cinematic
object lessons from nature. Our goal is
to produce and release these episodes
much more frequently. So please
prayerfully consider [music] partnering
with us so that we may continue to share
the hope of Jesus all over the world.
Thank [music] you so much for your
support. Aloha and Marina
Heat.
[music]
Heat. Heat.
Heat.
[music]
>> [music]
>> Heat. Heat.
Heat. Heat.
[music]
>> [music]
>> Heat. Heat. N.
[music]
>> [music]
>> Heat. Heat.
Heat. Heat.
here with us. If you are just join us
joining us for the first time today,
please put a one in the chat and please
let us know where you are viewing from.
We want to say a special welcome to you.
And if you didn't get a chance to put in
the chat during our first uh service
today and you're still viewing, please
put it in the chat where you're viewing
from so we can say a special welcome to
you too. We love to see where everybody
is coming from from all around the
world. Also want to just say happy new
year to all of you. This is our very
first Sabbath in 2026
and we are so thankful to the Lord for
living mana church for all of the
members all of the viewing audience all
of you who of you who pray and just come
and participate in the worship service
and in small groups all of those things
that you do here with Living Mana
Church. We are just so thankful to still
be here. We will be entering into our
fourth year officially on April 9th,
2026. But we are just thankful to be
getting closer and closer to that date
and just thankful for everything that
God does here for Living Mana Church.
Want to welcome Paul from Ottawa,
Canada. Welcome Paul. I'm sure it is
really cold right now in Canada. I'm
just assuming because I have been to
Canada in the winter and it was very
very very cold. But we are so w glad and
welcome you here to Living Man Church.
And we're just happy that you are here
with us. So please continue to put in
the chat where you are viewing from so
we can say a special welcome to you. We
have Okay. Devin Cook from Columbus,
Ohio. And Devin, I think it's probably
cold there, too, but I could be wrong.
We've been having like warm uh swings
here in the States. And so I don't know,
Ohio maybe and Columbus may be the same
thing. But welcome here to Living Mana
Church. It's good to have you here. So
again, if this is your very first time,
please put a one in the chat. Um, and
then we can say welcome to you, let you
know a little bit more about Living Mana
Church. Again, just want to say happy
new year to everyone. Welcome from
Norolk, Virginia. Good to have you here
at Living Mana Church. Um, so glad to to
see all of our viewing audience from all
around the states, not just from around
the world. Um, and so we have another uh
welcome from Columbus, Ohio. So, welcome
or or you're just saying happy Sabbath.
Okay, it's the same one. Happy Sabbath
back to you again uh there in Columbus,
Ohio. But again, I was just saying that
we are just so thankful to have
membership and viewing audience from all
around the world. I mentioned this uh
earlier that someone was watching from
Serbia. I think they said eastern Serbia
today. So when we see those things all
of when we see all your different
locations, it really does make us happy
and that we are just uh reaching uh
people all around the globe which is
just such a blessing to be able to do
that. We have Denise from Barbados.
Welcome. I'm sure it's very warm where
you are, Denise, versus maybe Canada um
in other parts of the world and the
country. Um want to uh say welcome to I
don't have a name, but Edenburgg, Texas.
Welcome to Living Man Church. It's very
good to have you here with us today. I
want to let you guys know um if you're
just visiting for the first time and you
didn't put a one, but it's your first
time, how you can stay connected to
Living Mana Church. And for those who
have been viewing us for a while and
still haven't signed up, this is always
a good reminder for you to be able to
stay connected to uh Living Mana Church.
So, one of the ways that you're going to
be able to do that if you're here in
North America is you'll be able to get
text alerts uh from Living Mana Church.
So that 855 number that you see there on
your screen, you can text LOC and to
that 855 number and you will
automatically
uh it'll automatically start signing you
up to get text alerts. And this is
helpful so that you will get alerts if
um if before we go live like 20 minutes
before we go live. So just in case you
forgot, you can prepare to go to be able
to view and to watch and um you'll be
able to get that alert. And also other
announcements and like when we send out
an announcement like hey we are doing um
we're doing question and answer for
Sabbath school this week. Send in your
questions. You will get that through
text. And so again that's only if you
are here in North America. I see in
Australia I know people are still saying
where they're viewing from. So I just
want to say welcome to you that's
viewing in Australia. I know it's your
Sunday mornings or middle maybe middle
of the night or maybe early early
morning in Australia. So, welcome. But
going back to our announcements, if
you're here in North America, you can uh
receive text alerts by signing up for
the 855 number. If you are in another
country, as you just saw, many of our
viewers are in all around the world. You
need to sign up for Mighty Networks.
Actually, those in America or North
America, you need to sign up for Mighty
Networks, too. This is our virtual
church home. you will get announcements
through mighty networks um like so that
you will know uh what's going on with
living mana church and um reminders
so that you can stay connected as well
um and and we also have our small group
so that is where you will be able to
build relationships in mighty networks
get to know people get to know our
viewing audience get to know our actual
official church members and so this is
where community is formed in mighty
networks and in the chat you will be
able to be there's a link there in the
chat. So just go up in the chat and you
will be able to sign up for mighty
networks by if you will just go in the
chat and just click that link and it
will start to sign you up. So whether
you are in North America or around the
world, you need to sign up for Mighty
Networks because that keeps you very
much so connected to us here at Living
Mana Church. So we are just so happy
that uh so many of you want to stay
connected to living manage church. So
definitely sign up for that. Also for
those of you who don't know but we do
have lamosci kids. So that's children's
programming and our children programming
is every uh Saturday morning or where
you are at it may not be morning but
11:30 central time. I should have never
said morning knowing that we have people
all around the world. Um but 11:30
central time it starts. And if you want
to get more information on how to sign
your child up, grandchild, niece,
nephew, or get more information about
it, you want to text kids to that 855
number and you will be able to get
information about LOCC kids. Also, you
can send an email to get more
information as well. And we have great
leadership that is leading out with LOCC
kids and our kids are learning some of
the powerful things that you learn in
your own adult Sabbath school. They're
learning in LOC kids but at a child's
level. So we are just excited to have
Loc Kids to be able to offer that to you
as well. If you are wanting to talk to
Pastor Myers and you want to set up a
virtual office hour,
if you want Okay. If you're wanting to
set up a virtual office appointment, you
can do that by emailing Patrice
livinga.live
and she will set that up for you so that
you'll be able to talk to Pastor Meyers.
Also, um if you are wanting to join
Living Mana Church or become a member,
you're going to use that same email
patrice at living.live. There's three
different ways you can become a member.
You can if you are a 7th Day Adventist
and a member of another church, you can
transfer your membership. If you are
just um learning about what Seventh Day
Adventists believe and you've been
baptized already, uh you will be able to
join by profession of faith. Um and the
same email that I just listed is how you
are able to uh set that up as well. And
then if you're needing to get baptized,
you use that same email to patrice
livinga.live live uh so that you can get
into Bible studies and pastor Myers will
baptize you. So those are the three
different ways that you can join Living
Mana Church or become a member of living
ma mana church. Also just want to let
you guys know and to remind you about
the power line. I know the power line
was uh live uh this week even on new on
New Year's Eve and I heard it was such a
blessing to so many. Um but we are live
at 800 PM Central Standard Time. Um it
has its own um YouTube channel. So we
are just so thankful for the power line
because what it does is they just pray.
So you put in your prayer request and
they're going to pray live over that
request. You can invite people to say,
"Hey, this is where you get your prayers
prayed over like immediately like right
there live." And if they don't want to
put it in the chat, you could say, "Hey,
I'll put your prayer request in the
chat." you can come and just listen as
people pray over your request. And so
that's 8:00 PM Central Standard Time um
on Wednesdays. And so that is a great uh
way to just um something you can just
extend to a friend or family members who
are needing prayer. Want to let you guys
know about something new that's
happening here at uh Living Mana Church.
We have a newsletter. It's a new year
and we have a brand new newsletter.
Um, and it's called Mana Connect. This
is the first edition. Uh, and we are so
excited. Couldn't be more thrilled to
share it with you. Mana connect is
designed to keep our living mana online
church family inspired, informed, and
connected with everything happening in
ministry. You can read it right now on
Mighty Networks. So, please go to Mighty
Networks and check it out, guys, or get
it delivered straight to you by text or
email, however you choose to receive it.
Don't miss out on this new way to stay
plugged in and and to what God is doing
with LMOC. The journey starts here.
Welcome to Mana Connect. So, we are
excited to have a new uh virtual
newsletter that's going to tell you
everything that's going on uh with
Living Mana Church. So definitely um
sign up to be sign up to get those
delivered to you in whatever way you
would like it to be delivered to you.
Also want to remind you guys about the
business directory. It's now open for
submissions and this is um from
Abraham's honorable dealing to the early
church's radical generosity. Scripture
affirms the power of believers
supporting one another in commerce. As
the remnant church, we continue this
legacy um strengthening the body of
Christ by hiring, investing in, and
uplifting uh the vocations of fellow
believers. A living mana business
resource directory is now available
within the mighty networks platform
under give mana. Church members and
friends who own a business are invited
to submit their listing by emailing uh
biz
living mana.urch church with your full
name, business name, and phone number.
So, we are excited to offer that to you
as well. We are needing volunteers.
Volunteers are needed. Start the year
serving the kingdom. It is your It is
your New Year's resolution. Sorry. If
There it is. If your New Year resolution
was to do more kingdom work, here's your
opportunity. Living Mana Online Church
is looking for volunteers to help
strengthen our ministry and serve the
body of Christ. All opportunities are
posted in the service opportunity
section in Mighty Networks. Take a
moment to explore where your gifts can
be used. Whether it's outreach,
communications, or behindthe-scenes
support, there's a place for you. Step
into 2026 with purpose. Serve, grow, and
build.
Also want to remind you guys about our
um youth LOC teens Friday night lights.
Every Friday, our LOC teens ages 13 to
18 come together on Zoom to welcome the
Sabbath. The best part, it's run by
teens for teens and a safe place to
grow, explore, and ask the real
questions that matter. Want to join?
Email for more information and the Zoom
link. Come connect, share, and discover
what it means to walk in faith with
friends your age who get it. All right,
that's exciting. Definitely share that
with a young person in that age group so
that they can be a part of that. Also
want to remind you guys of 10 minute
spotlight. As we begin the new year,
we're excited to spotlight the heart and
impact of our ministries, one story at a
time. Each feature will be a 10-minute
segment shared either through a live
interview or a pre-recorded submission
designed to showcase how each ministry
is serving, growing, and advancing God's
work. This is an opportunity for our
church family to see the vision,
mission, and fruit of each ministry in
action. To schedule your ministry
spotlight, please reach out to Gigi
Jones. Together, it's together. Let's
shine a light on what God is doing
through our ministries in 2026.
And so that's exciting. So you guys can
learn more about these ministries than
just me reading about them. Um here you
can actually um just hear more about the
ministries from the ministry leaders
themselves.
Also just want to remind you guys about
LLC Global. LMLC global is where we are
able to go around the world in seven
different languages. It is so exciting
to see uh we've had responses from
different uh people who speak some of
these different languages such positive
response and even the uh videos by
pastor Myers is going viral in some of
these languages. So, we just want to
share with you what that looks like and
how you are able to support continue to
support Living Mana Global.
[music]
>> [music]
>> Gloria
Gloria
Gloria.
Gloros [music]
[music]
Gloria Jesus Magnificant.
You observe.
Thank you for your prayers and your
support for Living Mana Global. Want to
tell you how you can continue uh to
support this ministry here at LMOC um in
general and also uh Living Mana Global.
The way you're able to uh financially
support and to keep this ministry going
is by going to Adventist giving and you
would put in Living Manage Church, click
in the right hand corner and you will
see a virtual tithe envelope um appear
in front of you and you're able to give
your tithe and your offering in this
way. So your tithe goes to the
Northeastern Conference, which Living
Matter Church is a church within that
conference. And so that helps to support
the conference and the worldwide church
of 7th Day Adventist. And then where you
see local church budget, that helps to
support what we're doing here at Living
Mana Church. And so the um living mana
global um and all the different things
that we're doing the benevolence fund
the keeping the studio um in topnotch
shape because we are online so we have
to be broadcast ready at always and have
a high quality. So the when you are
giving and supporting living manage
church and giving uh to the local church
budget that's helping us there. Um and
also um with the benevolence fund, we're
able to help others when they are asking
for help from Living Mana Church, that
is all coming um from your giving to the
local church budget. If giving virtually
is not what you would like to do when
you would like to mail in uh your tithe
or offering to Living Manage Church, you
will do it by using that address that's
on your screen, the PO Box 428, Owens
Crossroads, Alabama 35763.
And when you send it, please put a
little note to let us know what is for
tithe, what is for offering, or another
area which I've mentioned, the
benevolence fund, living mana global.
There's so many things uh that you were
able to support here at Living Mana
Church. We just want to say thank you
for your faithfulness. Here we are at
the beginning of another year and Living
Mana Church is still here and that is
because of your prayers and because of
your financial gifts as well. That keeps
us going and we are so very thankful to
you for just answering God's call and
coming here to Living Man Church. You
don't have to be here. You could go to a
brick-and-mortar church. And some of you
have a hybrid. You go to your
brickandmortar church in the early part
of Sabbath and then you finish off your
Sabbath with with us. And we are
thankful for all of you who do it just
that way or however you um worship here
with Living Matter of Church. We are
just thankful that you are here. Whether
it's from the beginning of Sabbath
school or later in the day after you've
gone to a brick-andmortar church. Again,
we just appreciate your prayers, you
showing up here, you sharing about us.
This is how we are here in 2026. We
started in April 9th, 2022 and here we
are January 3rd, 2026. So, we are just
so thankful to be here uh to start
another year and just to do for living
mana to fulfill God's will and to go
into all the world and just teaching uh
people all around the world about his
love and his goodness. if you would just
bow your heads with me as we lift up a
prayer of thanksgiving to God.
Heavenly Father, Lord, I just want to
thank you uh for this very first Sabbath
in 2026. It is so special to be here
starting another year. You have been
good to all of us. We've all had hard
times in 2025, but we are still here.
We're still standing because of you,
God. So, we just thank you and we praise
you for all that you have done in our
lives. Lord, I want to lift up every
person that is viewing and who will
view. If they are having health issues,
Lord, I pray over them and ask that you
will bless them. I pray over the
marriages, if they are having is
struggles in their marriage, family
issues with their children. Lord, I pray
over them if they are in finan having
financial issues. Lord, I pray over them
and just ask that you will work their
situation out. Lord, show everyone that
is viewing at this time that you are
real and that you hear their prayers.
You're aware of their situation and you
are working in their situation to their
for their best ideal outcome for them.
And so Lord, we just we just praise you
for what you have done in the past for
us. We praise you for bringing us here
to the beginning of another year. And
Lord, I just want to lift up Pastor
Meyers. You know, he has been under the
weather, but he is here. And so he has a
message from you. He's excited about the
message. So we pray over his throat,
Lord, over him just feeling okay to
deliver it with the power that you have
given this message to him in, Lord. And
we just pray for your Holy Spirit to be
with all of us that we will receive it
in the way that you want us to receive
this message today. We ask all these
things in Jesus' name. Amen.
January seems to [music] stir something
in us.
Whether it's hope or renewal or [music]
courage,
there's a certain feeling in January of
potential,
even rebirth.
And into whatever [music] that stirring
feels like,
God speaks the words that matter most.
Behold, I am making all things new.
In our uncertainties,
in the moments that feel both exciting
and risky,
and in the parts of [music] our story we
wish we could rewrite,
God is making all things new.
We know that the same God who's been
faithful in every day behind us will
remain faithful in every day ahead.
So as we step into this new year, may we
do so with open hands and with [music]
hearts that long for his glory to be
seen by a watching world.
And may [music] we trust that God will
do what only he can do and what he loves
to do.
that he will indeed make all things new.
>> Lord,
I [music and singing]
will lift
my eyes
[singing] to the hills.
[music]
Knowing
[singing]
my help
is
coming for
you.
Your
peace [singing] you give me
in time
of the star.
[music]
You are
the source of my [music] strength.
the strength,
>> the strength of my life.
I lift my hands in [music and singing]
to
praise
you. [singing] You
are [music]
you are
the [music]
strength of my strength.
You [singing] are
the strength of my life. [music]
I lift my hands [singing] in
prayer. [music]
to
[music]
you
to
[music] you
amen.
[music]
Amen.
Here at Living Mana, we bear each
other's burdens. When you need support
or prayer, when you're feeling
discouraged
or alone or anxious,
you don't have to face life struggles
alone.
Let us come boldly unto the throne of
grace.
that we may obtain mercy and find grace
to help in our time of need.
The Lord is close to the brokenhearted
and saves those who are crushed in
spirit.
Here
at Living Mana, we bear each other's
burdens. When you need support or
prayer, when you're feeling [music]
discouraged
or alone or anxious,
you don't have to face life struggles
alone.
Let us come boldly unto the throne of
grace that we may obtain mercy and find
grace to help in our time of need.
The Lord is close to the brokenhearted
and saves those who are crushed in
spirit.